Finding Aid for Henry Carter Adams Papers, 1864-1924
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Henry Carter Adams Papers
1864-1924
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.
851790 Ac Aa 2
Professor of economics at University of Michigan, 1880-1921, statistician for the Interstate Commerce Commission, 1887-1911, developed standard accounting procedures for railroads. Papers include personal and professional correspondence, diaries, travel journals, drafts of books, letter books, reports and printed materials concerning his work with the Interstate Commerce Commission, his activities as an expert witness in railroad compensation and tax cases, and University of Michigan affairs.
30.3 linear feet
2 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Professor Henry Carter Adams, Jr. (donor no. 4029) and came to the library in accessions of 1963 and 1965, and of Thomas Adams (donor no. 4320, 4029 and came to the library primarily in 1966.
The collection is open to research.
Select portions of the Henry Carter Adams papers have been microfilmed. In the Contents List, series or files that have been filmed are annotated with the phrase "microfilm copy available." In most cases microfilm can be obtained through inter-library loan.
Henry Carter Adams was born in Davenport, Iowa, December 31, 1851, the son of the Reverend Ephraim and Elizabeth (Douglass) Adams. His parents were members of the "Iowa Band," a group of New England Congregationalists who went west to establish churches and colleges modelled after Eastern counterparts. After graduating from Iowa College (later Grinnell) in 1874, Adams matriculated at Andover Seminary (his father's alma mater) to prepare for the ministry. After one year, however, he decided against a ministerial career and in favor of advanced study in political economy. Entering Johns Hopkins he fell under the influence of Herbert Baxter Adams. In 1878 he received the first doctor of philosophy degree awarded by the new university and spent the following year studying in Europe. In 1880, Adams accepted his first teaching position, a joint appointment at Cornell University and the University of Michigan. Forced out of Cornell because of his "radical" economic theories, he took up permanent residence in Ann Arbor, remaining on the Michigan faculty until his retirement in 1921.
In 1887, Adams accepted additional responsibilities as a statistician for the Interstate Commerce Commission. With the reorganization of the Commission in 1907, Adams became head of a section charged with accounts and statistics, where he served until he retired from federal service in 1911. In these beginning years of government utility regulation, Adams developed a uniform system of railroad accounting essential to such regulation. After he left the Commission, Adams used his technical knowledge in serving as an "expert witness" in numerous railroad compensation and tax cases.
From 1913 to 1916 Adams served the Chinese government as a special consultant on railroad accounts and statistics, spending a year in China by government invitation. In his last years he concerned himself increasingly with the improvement and expansion of education in business and the social sciences. Several universities, recognizing his pioneering work, granted Adams honorary degrees. In 1895 his professional colleagues elected him president of the then infant American Economic Association. He also served for a time as associate editor of the International Journal of Ethics.
As a spokesman for progressive ideas, Henry Carter Adams demonstrated a penchant for practical innovation and controversy, lecturing extensively and writing numerous books and articles on a wide range of social, economic and philosophical issues and questions. He died August 11, 1921.
The Henry Carter Adams papers have been arranged into nine series representing either types of documents or areas of activities. These series are:
Correspondence
Student Notebooks and Diaries and other bound materials
U.S. Interstate Commerce Commission
Railroad and Utility Company Consultation Case files
Special Consultant to the Chinese Government
Addresses, Lectures and Writings
Miscellaneous
Topical file
Photographs.
The Henry Carter Adams papers consist of personal and professional correspondence, diaries, travel journals, drafts of books, letter books, reports and printed materials concerning his work with the Interstate Commerce Commission, his activities as an expert witness in railroad compensation and tax cases, and University of Michigan affairs.
Subjects:
Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Company.; Canadian Express Company (Montrèal, Quèbec); Canadian Northern Express Company (Toronto, Ont.); Chicago and Alton Railroad Company.; Chicago & Eastern Illinois Railroad Company.; Chicago, Cincinnati and Louisville Railroad Company.; Chicago Demurrage Bureau.; Chicago, Indianapolis, and Louisville Railway.; Chicago, Milwaukee and St. Paul Railway Company.; Chicago, Peoria and St. Louis Railroad Company of Illinois.; Chicago Warehouse & Terminal Company.; China--History--1861-1912.; Cleveland, Cincinnati, Chicago, and St. Louis Railway Company.; Colorado and Southern Railway.; Detroit (Mich.); Detroit United Railway.; Economics.; Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Erie Railroad.; Galveston, Harrisburg & San Antonio Railway Company.; Germany.; Great Northern Express Company.; Great Northern Railway Company (U.S.); Houston & Texas Central Railway Company.; Houston, East and West Texas Railway.; Houston and Shreveport Railroad Company.; Illinois Central Railroad Company.; Illinois Tunnel Company.; International & Great Northern Railroad.; Iowa Central Railway Company.; Kansas City Southern Railway.; Lagonda Western Railway Company.; Lehigh Valley Railroad.; Louisville and Nashville Railroad Company.; Louisiana & Pacific Railway Company.; Louisiana and Texas Railroad and Steamship Company.; Louisiana Western Railroad Company.; Manufacturers' Railway Company.; Michigan. Board of State Tax Commissioners.; Minneapolis & St. Louis Railroad.; Missouri, Kansas and Texas Railway Company.; Missouri Pacific Railroad Company.; Nashville, Chattanooga and St. Louis Railway.; New Orleans, Natchez & Northwestern Railroad Company of Louisiana.; New York Central Railroad Company.; Northern Express Company (St. Paul, Minn.); Oregon Railway and Navigation Company.; Union Pacific Oregon Shortline Railroad.; Pennsylvania Railroad.; Pullman Company.; Public utilities--United States.; Railroads--United States.; St. Louis-San Francisco Railway Company.; St. Louis Southwestern Railway Company.; San Pedro, Los Angeles & Salt Lake Railroad Company.; Social service--United States--Societies, etc.; Southern Pacific Company.; Southern Railway (U.S.); Street-railroads--United States.; Taxation--United States.; Texarkana and Fort Smith Railway Company.; Texas & Pacific Railway.; Toledo, St. Louis, and Western Railroad Company.; Trunk Line Association.; Union Pacific Railroad Company.; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission.; Universities and colleges--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Economics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.Faculty.; Waterloo, Cedar Falls and Northern Railway Company.; Western Express Company (Toronto, Ont.); Western Railway Weighing Association and Inspection Bureau.
Contributors:
Adams, Bertha H. Wright.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Adams, Elizabeth Sylvia Ann (Douglass), 1821-1905.; Adams, Ephraim, 1818-1907.; Adams, Ephraim Douglass, 1865-1930.; Adams, Herbert Baxter, 1850-1901.; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; Allison, William B. (William Boyd), 1829-1908.; Anderson, William J.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Ashley, H. W.; Baker, Ray Stannard, 1870-1946.; Bartlett, Hamilton H.; Beakes, Samuel Willard, 1861-1927.; Bemis, Edward Webster, 1860-1930.; Brandeis, Louis Dembitz, 1856-1941.; Brown, W. C. (William Carlos), 1853-1924.; Bullock, Charles Jesse, 1869-1941.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Butterfield, Kenyon L. (Kenyon Leech), 1868-1935.; Canfield, James Hulme, 1847-1909.; Clark, Frederick Converse.; Clark, John Bates, 1847-1938.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Commons, John Rogers, 1862-1945.; Conant, Charles A. (Charles Arthur), 1861-1915.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Cooley, Lyman Edgar, 1850-1917.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Dawson, William Mercer Owens, 1853-1916.; Dewey, Davis Rich, 1858-1942.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Dixon, Frank Haigh, 1869-1944; D'Ooge, Martin Luther, 1839-1915.; Durand, Edward Dana, b. 1871.; Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.; Elkins, Stephen B. (Stephen Benton), 1841-1911.; Ely, Richard Theodore, 1854-1943.; Evans, Elizabeth Edson Gibson, 1832-1911.; Fairchild, Fred Rogers, 1877-1966.; Fetter, Frank A. (Frank Albert), 1863-1949.; Fisher, Irving, 1867-1947.; Friday, David, 1876-1945.; Giddings, Franklin Henry, 1855-1931.; Fuertes, E. A.; Gifford, Walter S. (Walter Sherman), 1885-1966; Gilman, Daniel Coit, 1831-1908.; Gore, Mr. (Thomas Pryor), 1870-1949.; Gray, John H. (John Henry), 1859-1946; Guthe, Karl Eugen, 1866-1915.; Hadley, Arthur Twining, 1856-1930.; Hanshue, J. J.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.; Hathaway, F. R.; Hawes, Harry B.; Hawley, Willis Chatman.; Hill, Robert Thomas, 1858-1941.; Hollander, Jacob Harry, 1871-1940.; Hopkins, Albert J. (Albert Jarvis), 1846-1922.; Hull, Charles Henry, b. 1864.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; James, Edmund J. (Edmund Janes), 1855-1925.; Jameson, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1859-1937.; Jeffery, Edward Turner, 1843-1927.; Jenks, Jeremiah Whipple, 1856-1929.; Johnson, Emory R. (Emory Richard), 1864-1950.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Jruks, J. W.; Knight, George W. (George Wells), 1858-1932.; Labadie, Jo, 1850-1933.; Lathrop, Julia Clifford, 1858-1932.; Laughlin, J. Laurence (James Laurence), 1850-1933.; Lawton, Charles De Witt, 1835-1909.; Lewis, David J. (David John), 1869-1952.; Manny, Frank Addison, 1868-1954.; Martin, H. B.; Mayo-Smith, Richmond, 1854-1901.; Mead, Edwin Doak, 1849-1937.; Newcomb, H. T. (Harry Turner), 1867-1944.; Ono, Yeijiro.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), b. 1860.; Page, Walter Hines, 1855-1918.; Paxson, Frederic L. (Frederic Logan), 1877-1948.; Peabody, Charles.; Pickard, Josiah Little, 1824-1914.; Raymond, J. Everett.; Ripley, William Zebina, 1867-1941.; Rogers, Henry Wade, 1853-1926.; Rosenthal, Lessing, 1868-1949.; Salter, William Mackintire, 1853-1931.; Sanborn, F. B. (Franklin Benjamin), 1831-1917.; Sedgwick, W. T. (William Thompson), 1855-1921.; Seligman, Edwin Robert Anderson, 1861-1939.; Sharfman, I. Leo (Isaiah Leo), 1886-1969; Shaw, Albert, 1857-1947.; Shibley, George H. (George Henry), b. 1861.; Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.; Smith, Henry Cassorte, 1859-1911.; Smith, J. Allen (James Allen), 1860-1926.; Smith, John McMunn C., 1853-1923.; Stanley, Augustus Owsley, 1867-1958.; Stearns, Justus S. (Justus Smith), b. 1845.; Stephens, E. W.; Taussig, F. W. (Frank William), 1859-1940.; Taylor, Graham, 1851-1938.; Thomas, Calvin, 1854-1919.; Towne, Charles Arnette, 1858-1928.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Tunell, George Gerard.; Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; Van Hise, Charles Richard, 1857-1918.; Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.; Veblen, Thorstein, 1857-1929.; Ward, Lester Frank, 1841-1913.; Wells, David Ames, 1828-1898.; Wheeler, Benjamin Ide, 1854-1927.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Wilcox, Delos F. (Delos Franklin), 1873-1928.; Wilcox, Walter Francis, 1861-; Williams, John Sharp, 1854-1932.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.
Visual materials - Subjects:
Adams, Bertha H. Wright.; Adams, Elizabeth Sylvia Ann (Douglass), 1821-1905.; Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; Adams, Henry Carter, 1891-1970.; Adams, Theodore Wright, 1896-; Adams, Thomas Hammond, 1901-; Adams family.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Children.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Private libraries.; Travel.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  he Correspondence series, dating from 1864 to 1925 (with the inclusion of scattered materials following his death), includes both letters received and letterpress volumes of copies of letters sent. Correspondence for 1881-1902 and 1903-1907 has been microfilmed. The letterpress volumes represent Adams' professional correspondence while a faculty member at the University of Michigan. Letterpress volumes from his service with the Interstate Commerce Commission will be found in that series. A selective name inventory of the correspondents in the Adams collections can be found at the end of this finding aid.
  - 1864-June 1883 (Box 1)
  - July 1883-March 1890 (Box 2)
  - April 1890-January 1896 (Box 3)
  - February 1896-February 1899 (Box 4)
  - March 1899-1901 (Box 5)
  - 1902-March 1904 (Box 6)
  - April 1904-March 1906 (Box 7)
  - April 1906-1909 (Box 8)
  - 1910-March 1911 (Box 9)
  - April 1911-June 1916 (Box 10)
  - July 1916-June 1920 (Box 11)
  - July 1920-May 1925 (Box 12)
  - Undated, 8 folders (Box 12)
  - undated, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Correspondence of Professor David Friday, 1912-1919 (Box 13)
  - Letters written from China by HCA and his wife to their son, Carter, 1913-1915 (Box 13)
  - Letters of son Theodore Adams exchanged with his parents and grandparents, 1898-1914 (Box 13)
  - Letters of son Thomas Adams exchanged with his parents and grandparents, 1901-1915 (Box 13)
  - Letterbooks
    - October 1893-January 1896 (Box 13)
    - January 1896-March 1899 (Box 13)
    - April 1899-October 1900 (Box 13)
    - October 1900-March 1902 (Box 13)
    - March 1902-July 1903 (Box 14)
    - July 1903-February 1906 (Box 14)
    - 1895-1900 (Box 14)
      (Michigan Political Science Association secretary's correspondence)
- Student Notebooks, Diaries and other bound materials
  The Student Notebooks, Diaries and other bound materials series consists of bound volumes of diaries and notes and notebooks from the period when Adams was a student at Iowa College, then at Andover Seminary. There are also diaries and notes from his stay in Germany, 1878-1879, other diaries from 1882, and various other notebooks. This series is arranged chronologically and dates from 1870 to 1884 with one non-Adams account book from the period of 1922-1923.
  - Student notebook on Roman history, 1870-1874 (Box 14)
  - Diary, 1871 (Box 14)
  - Diary and student notes, 1873-1882 (Box 14)
  - Andover Seminary notes, 1875 (Box 14)
  - Andover Seminary student notes, 1875-1877 (Box 14)
  - Essay on taxation, circa 1875-1877 (Box 14)
  - Andover diary and notes, 1875-1877 (Box 14)
  - Diary, 1878 (Box 15)
  - Stuttgart notes, circa 1884 (Box 15)
    (more probably notes for Taxation in United States or Science of Finance)
  - Berlin diary, 1878-1879 (Box 15)
  - Berlin notes, 1879 (Box 15)
  - Subjects for essay with bibliography, 1880 (Box 15)
  - Diary, 1882 (Box 15)
  - Lectures on taxation by Thomas M. Cooley, 1882 (Box 15)
  - Academic notes, 1884 (Box 15)
  - Account book, 1922-1923 (Box 15)
- U.S. Interstate Commerce Commission
  The Interstate Commerce Commission series covering the period of Adams time with the ICC (1887-1911), though it does include some volumes of administrative reports and instructions, consists primarily of two subseries. The first is a file of reports arranged alphabetically by the name of railroad or the railroad-related agency. The second is a sequence of letterpress volumes of correspondence sent by Adams while with the ICC. These volumes date from 1889 to 1911.
  - Classification of Operating Expenses, 1889 (Box 15)
  - Book of Instruction for Annual Report, 1889 (Box 15)
  - Manuscript volume of statistics presented by Elmer Walker (Box 15)
  - Instructions to Examiners (Box 15)
  - Reports (by name of company or agency)
    - Atlantic Coast Line Company (Box 15)
    - Canadian Express Company at Montreal, Canada (Box 15)
    - Canadian Northern Express Company at Toronto, Canada (Box 15)
    - Chicago and Alton Railroad Company and Illinois Central Railroad Company (Box 15)
    - Chicago Demurrage Bureau (Box 15)
    - Chicago, Cincinnati and Louisville Railway Company (Box 15)
    - Chicago, Indianapolis and Louisville Railway Company (Box 15)
    - Chicago, Milwaukee and St. Paul Railway Company (Box 15)
    - Chicago, Peoria and St. Louis Railway Company (Box 15)
    - Cleveland, Cincinnati, Chicago and St. Louis Railway Company (Box 16)
    - Colorado and Southern Railway Company (Box 16)
    - Conference of Examiners of the Bureau of Statistics and Accounts (Box 16)
    - Erie Railroad Company (Box 16)
    - Free Transportation: Special Report in the Matter of Free Transportation Furnished by Carriers (Box 16)
    - Galveston, Harrisburg and San Antonio Railroad (Box 16)
    - Grain Shipper at Cincinnati, Ohio, 1907-1908 (Box 16)
    - Great Northern Express Company (Box 16)
    - Great Northern Railway (Box 16)
    - Houston and Texas Central Railroad Company; Houston East and West Texas Railway Company; Houston and Shreveport Railroad Company (Box 16)
    - Illinois Central Railroad Company (Box 16)
    - Illinois Tunnel Company and the Chicago Warehouse and Terminal Company (Box 16)
    - International and Great Northern Railroad Company (Box 16)
    - Iowa Central Railway Company (Box 16)
    - Joint Rate Inspection Bureau (Box 16)
    - Kansas City Southern Railway Company and the Texarkana and Fort Smith Railway Company (Box 16)
    - Lagonda Western Railway Company (Box 16)
    - Lehigh Valley Railroad Company (Box 16)
    - Louisiana and Pacific Railway Company (Box 16)
    - Louisville and Nashville Railroad (Box 16)
    - Manufacturers' Railway Company of St. Louis (Box 16)
    - Michigan, Indiana and Illinois Line (Box 16)
    - Minneapolis and St. Louis Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - Missouri, Kansas and Texas Railway (Box 17)
    - Missouri Pacific Railway System (Box 17)
    - Morgan's Louisiana and Texas Railroad and Steamship Company; Louisiana Western Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - Nashville, Chattanooga and St. Louis Railway Company (Box 17)
    - New Orleans and Northwestern Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - New York Central Railroad Lines (Box 17)
    - Northern Express Company at St. Paul, Minnesota (Box 17)
    - Oregon Railroad and Navigation Company (Box 17)
    - Oregon Short Line Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad, Pennsylvania Lines West of Pittsburgh (Box 17)
    - Pullman Company: Chicago and Alton Railroad Company and the Illinois Central Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - St. Louis and San Francisco Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - St. Louis Southwestern Railroad Company (Box 17)
    - San Pedro, Los Angeles and Salt Lake Railroad Company (Box 18)
    - Sault Ste. Marie Bridge Company (Box 18)
    - Southern Railway Company (Box 18)
    - "Tap Line" Hearing at New Orleans (Box 18)
    - Texas and Pacific Railway Company (Box 18)
    - Toledo, St. Louis and Western Railroad Company (Box 18)
    - Track Changes at Gary, Indiana for U.S. Steel (Box 18)
    - Trunk Line Association (Box 18)
    - Southern Pacific Company, Union Pacific Railroad Company, Oregon Short Line Railroad Company, Oregon Railroad and Navigation Company (Box 18)
    - Waterloo, Cedar Falls and Northern Railway (Box 18)
    - Western Express Company at Toronto, Canada (Box 18)
    - Western Railway Weighing Association and Inspection Bureau (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous Reports, Memoranda, Charts (Box 18)
  - Letterbooks (Box 19)
    - 1889-1892 (Box 19)
    - 1891-1893 (Box 19)
    - 1891-1894 (Box 19)
    - 1892-1893 (Box 19)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 19)
    - 1894-1895 (Box 19)
    - 1895-1896 (Box 19)
    - 1896-1899 (Box 19)
    - 1899-1900 (Box 19)
    - 1900-1901 (Box 20)
    - 1901-1903 (Box 20)
    - 1903-1904 (Box 20)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 20)
    - 1908-1909 (Box 20)
    - 1909-1910 (Box 20)
    - 1910 (Box 20)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 20)
- Railroad and Utility Company Consultation Case files
  The Railroad and Utility Company Consultation Case files include reports, memoranda, and other working materials from a variety of tax and appraisal cases for which Adams was a consultant.
  - American and Telephone and Telegraph Company (Box 21)
  - Carolina, Clinchfield and Ohio Railway (Box 21)
  - Chicago Smoke Abatement Case (Box 21)
  - Chicago Sanitation Drainage Canal Case (Box 21)
  - Detroit United Railway (Box 21)
  - Detroit United Railway (cont.) (Box 22)
  - Duluth, South Shore and Atlantic Railway Company (Box 23)
  - Illinois Central Railroad Company and Illinois Charter Tax Case (Box 23)
  - Kansas City Southern Railway Company (Box 23)
  - Michigan Central Railroad (Box 23)
  - Michigan Railroad Appraisal Case (Box 23)
  - Michigan Railroad Tax Case (Box 23)
  - New Jersey Public Service Railway (Box 23)
  - New York Central Railroad Company (Box 23)
  - Railway Mail Pay Case (Box 23)
  - Western Pacific Railroad (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous Material (Box 24)
- Special Consultant to the Chinese Government
  The Special Consultant to the Chinese Government series includes a scattering of collected material on Chinese railroads from the period 1913-1916.
  - Miscellaneous materials on Chinese railroads (Box 24)
- Addresses, Lectures and Writings
  The Addresses, Lectures, Writings series consists of three subseries for addresses, lectures, and manuscripts of writings. Included here as well are volumes of Adams' published essays and addresses.
  - Addresses
    - The Doctrine of Capital (Box 25)
    - The economics of arbitration (Box 25)
    - Historic background of the labor movement (Box 25)
    - Is civilization just to working men (Box 25)
    - On the meaning of industrial history (Box 25)
    - Opening address for School of Applied Ethics (Box 25)
    - The outlook for federal railway legislation (Box 25)
    - The outlook of a political economist (Box 25)
    - Relation of church to working man (Box 25)
    - Remarks on occasion of presentation of portrait of Ephraim Adams to Grinell College (Box 25)
    - The right of employment (Box 25)
    - Social significance of machinery (Box 25)
    - Socialism (Box 25)
    - Trusts (Box 25)
    - Trusts (Box 25)
      (address presented before American Economic Association)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 25)
  - Lectures (alphabetical by title)
    - Analysis of economic thought (Box 25)
      [microfilm copy available]
    - Austrian School of Economy (Box 25)
    - Communism and socialism (Box 25)
    - Current economic problems, 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Fluctuation of prices from 1782-1865 (Box 25)
    - Free trade (Box 25)
    - Immigration (Box 25)
    - Industrial history (Box 25)
    - An interpretation of the movement of our times (Box 25)
    - Labor (Box 25)
    - Labor and monopoly problem (Box 25)
    - Outline of lectures on social and industrial problems (Box 25)
    - Panics and commercial depressions (Box 25)
    - Railway problems (Box 25)
    - School of Applied Ethics (Box 25)
    - Social and industrial reform (Box 25)
    - Social movements (Box 25)
    - Taxation, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Transportation (Box 26)
    - Trusts (Box 26)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 26)
  - Writings
    - First Period of State Indebtedness. Revolutionary Period (Box 26)
    - Outline of Political Economy, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Public debt, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - Public industries and the fiscal policy, 2 folders (Box 26)
    - Railway accounting, 5 folders (Box 26)
    - Science of finance, 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Survey of the American taxing system (Box 27)
    - Taxation in the United States, 1789-1816, thesis, Johns Hopkins University (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 27)
    - Articles and reprints of articles by HCA, 1 folders (Box 27)
    - Collected essays and addresses, 1 volumes (Box 27)